<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Talks | يوسف</title>
    <link>/talk/</link>
      <atom:link href="/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Talks</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Talks</title>
      <link>/talk/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The arithmetic of pairing-based proof systems</title>
      <link>/talk/phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my PhD defense.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing cryptographic algorithms in gnark</title>
      <link>/talk/devcon6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/devcon6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This talk is about algorithmic optimizations techniques used in gnark. In particular, we show that the implementation of Multi-Scalar-Multiplication (MSM) is 45% faster compared to competitors libraries. We also explain optimizations in the pairing computations both out-circuit and in-circuit. To the best of our knowledge, these implementations are best-in-class.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elliptic curves and zk-SNARKs</title>
      <link>/talk/rennes_seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/rennes_seminar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A proof system is a protocol where one party (called the prover) tries to convince another party (called the verifier) that a given statement is true. In the class of non-interactive proof systems, a particularly interesting concept for proving the computational integrity is the Succinct Non-interactive ARgument of Knowledge (SNARK). It provides a computationally sound proof, cheap to verify and small compared to the size of the statement or the witness. Bilinear pairings over elliptic curves have become key ingredients for instantiating such SNARKs. In this thesis we investigate tailored pairing-friendly elliptic curves to efficiently implement SNARKs. We present a study at three stages of the process: curves to instantiate a SNARK, curves to instantiate a recursive SNARK, and also curves to express an elliptic-curve related statement. We provide new constructions of curves for SNARKs and new families of 2-chain curves for recursive SNARKs. We derive and implement in open-source efficient algorithms to speed up the arithmetic on these curves: Co-factor clearing, subgroup membership testing, multi-scalar multiplication and pairings over 2-chains. We also study and optimize elliptic curves arithmetic and pairings as a SNARK statement, yielding to the fastest recursive proof generation in pairing-based settings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cofactor clearing and subgroup membership testing on pairing-friendly elliptic curves</title>
      <link>/talk/africacrypt22/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/africacrypt22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An important cryptographic operation on elliptic curves is hashing to a point on the curve. When the curve is not of prime order, the point is multiplied by the cofactor so that the result has a prime order. This is important to avoid small subgroup attacks for example.  A second important operation, in the composite-order case, is testing whether a point belongs to the subgroup of prime order. A pairing is a bilinear map e: G1×G2 → GT where G1 and G2 are distinct subgroups of prime order r of an elliptic curve, and GT is a multiplicative subgroup of the same prime order r of a finite field extension.  Pairing-friendly curves are rarely of prime order. In this talk, we investigate cofactor clearing and subgroup membership testing on these composite-order curves. First, we generalize a result on faster cofactor clearing for BLS curves to other pairingfriendly families of a polynomial form from the taxonomy of Freeman, Scott and Teske. Second, we investigate subgroup membership testing for G1 and G2. We fix a proof argument for the G2 case that appeared in a preprint by Scott in late 2021 and has recently been implemented in different cryptographic libraries. We then generalize the result to both G1 and G2 and apply it to different pairing-friendly families of curves.  This gives a simple and shared framework to prove membership tests for both cryptographic subgroups.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Families of SNARK-friendly 2-chains of elliptic curves</title>
      <link>/talk/eurocrypt22/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/eurocrypt22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk, we first are interested in families of 2-chains in which the BW6-761 curve would fall. We present a family of BW6 curves from any BLS12 curve and derive generic formulas, in terms of the BLS12 curve seed u, and integer parameters ht,hy. We extend this work to a 2-chain family of BW6 curves from BLS24 curves. To achieve higher levels of security in the target finite field of the outer curves, we compare a larger field characteristic thanks to larger parameters ht,hy, to the larger embedding degrees 8 and 12 obtained with Cocks-Pinch curves. Finally, we argue that the BLS12 and BLS24 based families are respectively tailored for Groth’16 and KZG-based SNARKs recursive proof composition, and we present a short list of curves with an optimized implementation along with benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elliptic curves and SNARKs</title>
      <link>/talk/aarhus_seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/aarhus_seminar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Elliptic curves have become key ingredients for instantiating zero-knowledge proofs and more generally proof systems. Recently, there have been many tailored constructions of these curves that aim at efficiently implementing different kinds of proof systems. In this talk we provide a comprehensive view on existing work. We present an overview at two stages of the process; curves to instantiate a SNARK and curves to instantiate a recursive SNARK.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pairings in R1CS</title>
      <link>/talk/zksummit7/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/zksummit7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This presentation is about how to efficiently express a pairing a Rank-1 Constraint System (R1CS) arithmetic circuit. The goal is to reduce the time complexity to SNARK prove a bilinear pairing. A corresponding research paper will be soon available on ePrint.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Families of SNARK-friendly 2-chains of elliptic curves</title>
      <link>/talk/jc2-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/jc2-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this talk, we first are interested in families of 2-chains in which the BW6-761 curve would fall. We present a family of BW6 curves from any BLS12 curve and derive generic formulas, in terms of the BLS12 curve seed u, and integer parameters ht,hy. We extend this work to a 2-chain family of BW6 curves from BLS24 curves. To achieve higher levels of security in the target finite field of the outer curves, we compare a larger field characteristic thanks to larger parameters ht,hy, to the larger embedding degrees 8 and 12 obtained with Cocks-Pinch curves. Finally, we argue that the BLS12 and BLS24 based families are respectively tailored for Groth’16 and KZG-based SNARKs recursive proof composition, and we present a short list of curves with an optimized implementation along with benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On choosing suitable elliptic curves for zk-SNARK</title>
      <link>/talk/caramba_seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/caramba_seminar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This presentation is about requirements and methods to contruct tailored and optimized elliptic curves for zkSNARK applications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>zk-SNARK 101</title>
      <link>/talk/oisillons_gt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/oisillons_gt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This presentation is an introduction to the concept of zkSNARKs alongside an step-by-step toy example of Pinocchio-ish zkSNARK protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimized and secure pairing-friendly elliptic curve suitable for one layer proof composition</title>
      <link>/talk/cans2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/cans2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This presentation is about a joint paper with &lt;a href=&#34;https://members.loria.fr/AGuillevic/&#34;&gt;Aurore Guillevic&lt;/a&gt; that can be found online &lt;a href=&#34;https://eprint.iacr.org/2021/1359&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It proposes new families of elliptic curves that are tailored and optimized for recursive SNARKs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Faster proof composition with the BW6-761 curve</title>
      <link>/talk/ey_summit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/ey_summit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This presentation is about using the BW6-761 curve to generate and verify faster composed Groth&#39;16 zk-SNARK proofs and its application in EY Blockchain effort to privacy-preserving blockchains.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimized and secure pairing-friendly elliptic curve suitable for one layer proof composition</title>
      <link>/talk/zksummit5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/zksummit5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This presentation is about a joint paper with &lt;a href=&#34;https://members.loria.fr/AGuillevic/&#34;&gt;Aurore Guillevic&lt;/a&gt; that can be found online &lt;a href=&#34;https://eprint.iacr.org/2020/351&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It introduced a new elliptic curve, namely &lt;strong&gt;BW6-761&lt;/strong&gt; that is very efficient for one-layer recursive SNARKs compared to the state-of-the-art.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nightfall - The Open Source Privacy Solution for Ethereum</title>
      <link>/talk/devcon5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/devcon5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We believe that public blockchain is the future of business to business transactions. However, two issues - privacy and scalability - will need to be solved if this vision is to be fully realised. This talk will explain the motivations behind the open-source nightfall code and how it is intended to tackle the first of these issues. We cover the operation of the protocol, the method by which it provides complete privacy, and how developers can use it to build their own applications by making use of its smart contract infrastructure and the ZoKrates framework. We will also present our modelling of transaction costs, which shows that nightfall can already provide a cost-competitive alternative to private blockchains for many situations and how that will be true for a growing number of use cases in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elliptic curves in cryptography</title>
      <link>/talk/zk_par1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/zk_par1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I this presentation the 4th of July in Paris during ZK-PAR 0x01, the first Zero Knowledge meetup in the french capital. The meetups started in Tel-Aviv and then London and now Paris. They are intended for anyone interested in applied cryptography for privacy-preserving technology. The presentations are usually focussed on technical and practical aspects of this technology, notably its relation to blockchain technology. You can find more information and community discussions in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/groups/800441673459620/&#34;&gt;Facebook group&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCl6oyLa4CblZRurgwZwpgPQ&#34;&gt;Youtube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ZK-PAR 0x01 hosted two speakers, Bastien Teinturier and myself. Bastien talked about anonymous payments in Bitcoin’s Lightning network and I invite you to watch his &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NM6WQkdjvYw&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; and go through his &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/download/1117672475092357/ZK-PAR%200x01%20-%20Anonymous%20Payments%20in%20the%20Lightning%20Network%20-%20Bastien%20Teinturier.pdf?av=1151079687&amp;amp;eav=AfZveN272Vcrq3TdwQjKZQC-0UB7Q5NrjhkqP49rdEu0fBxPOFQZ55mNASEgwNbfSFI&amp;amp;hash=AcruoDF8Elw9chP1&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
